Bruno Baère Pedrazzi Lomba de Araujo

mail: bruno.baere@gmail.com phone: 🚳 +5521996826336 / 💽 +14385261793

SUMMARY

I am motivated by challenging tasks and to teach others about what I have learned. My experience as both an academic researcher and as a systems analyst helps me to approach, to model, to understand problems, and to develop a solution. My analytical skills have been proven useful in detecting and preventing bugs and problems in systems modeling.

PROFESSIONAL Technical Lead

Feb 2022 - Present

EXPERIENCE

Instituto Tecgraf – PUC-Rio, Computational Geophysics Group

Tech lead in v3o2 project. Responsible for software architecture decisions for one of the teams. Programming in C++17.

Senior Systems Analyst

Feb 2020 - Feb 2022

Instituto Tecgraf – PUC-Rio, Computational Geophysics Group

C++ developer in v3o2 project. Programming in C++ 17 using Qt, GTK+, boost on Linux CentOS 7. Version control in git and CI/CD with GitLab. Worked in a remote (work from home) environment, using VPN and SSH, coordinating using Jira and Slack.

Product Owner Feb 2018 - Jan 2020

Instituto Tecgraf – PUC-Rio, Computational Geophysics Group

Product Owner in v3o2 project. Responsible for the product value of various parts of the software dealing with geology and geophysics. Responsibilities included: understanding the client's needs, proposing a solution, creating user stories for the development team, and managing client expectations. I also wrote and maintained the product manual for the parts I was responsible for, and helped restructuring the recruitment interview process.

Senior Systems Analyst / Researcher

 ${
m Aug}~2011$ - ${
m Feb}~2018$

Instituto Tecgraf – PUC-Rio, Computational Geophysics Group

C++ developer in v3o2 project, a seismic and well data visualizer for Petrobras running on RedHat/CentOS 5 using OpenGL, GTK+, boost, and Qt. For QA used GoogleTest framework, valgrind, and cppcheck. I organized and wrote the documentation of the development environment setup for home office, and worked on the upgrade to RedHat/CentOS 6. I also presented with colleagues a 2-day workshop on Scrum for team members.

Researcher

Apr 2009 - Aug 2011

ICAD/Visionlab – PUC-Rio

Researcher in games, digital entertainment and simulations. C# programmer in a joint project with CENPES and USP. Developed a shade tree editor in C# and Windows GDI for building DirectX shaders for the proof tank visualizer project.

Undergraduate teaching assistant

Mar 2009 - Dec 2009

Department of Computer Science – PUC-Rio

Worked as UTA for Introduction to Programming (C language) and Data Structures. Gave extra classes on Saturdays and post-class hours, resolving exercises and exams.

Intern Oct 2008 - Mar 2009

ICA - Laboratório de Inteligência Computacional Aplicada - PUC-Rio

C# developer. Worked at FxANEEL project, developing part of the user interface with WindowsForms and XML. Developed a wrapper for GSLIB library in C# and created the model for library documentation used by the lab.

Scientific Initiation

Aug 2006 - Aug 2008

ICAD/Visionlab – PUC-Rio

Development of a simulation library for Torque Game Engine. Researched game engine use in fluid simulations, programmed in C++ using OGRE rendering engine. Granted 2 years of CNPQ scholarship.

PUBLICATIONS Maria das G. de A. Chagas, Bruno B. P. L. de Araujo, Waldecir V. Faria, Cezar G. Loureiro, Maria I. M. M. Carmo, Nelson J. Donato, Tathiana S. T. Silva, Victoria D. Maidantchik, Yann L. M. de M. Marques. Design de Jogos de RPG Digitais: Uma investigação sobre a experiência de jogo. In: Proceedings of the XIV Brazilian Symposium on Games and Digital Entertainment (SBGames 2015), Teresina, Piauí, Brazil, November 2015.

> Paula C. Ribeiro, Bruno B. P. L. de Araujo, Alberto Raposo. ComFiM: A Cooperative Serious Game to Encourage the Development of Communicative Skills between Children with Autism. In: Proceedings of the XIII Brazilian Symposium on Computer Games and Digital Entertainment (SBGames 2014), Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil, November 2014. DOI: 10.1109/SBGAMES.2014.19

> Bruno B. P. L. de Araujo, Bruno Feijó. Evaluating dynamic difficulty adaptivity in shoot'em up games. In: Proceedings of the XII Brazilian Symposium on Computer Games and Digital Entertainment (SBGames 2013), São Paulo, Brazil, October 2013.

EDUCATION

M.Sc. in Computer Science, Computer Graphics

2010 - 2012

Pontifícia Universidade Católica do Rio de Janeiro - PUC-Rio

Advisor: Bruno Feijó

Dissertation title: A study on dynamic difficulty adaptivity for shoot'em up games

Granted 2 years of CAPES scholarship

GPA: 3.54 (4.0 scale)

B.Sc. in Computer Engineering

2005 - 2009

Pontifícia Universidade Católica do Rio de Janeiro - PUC-Rio

Minor: Advanced studies in Mathematics

Final project title: A shade tree editor for OGRE materials

Granted 2 years of CNPQ scholarship

Language proficiency: Cambridge English FCE grade B2

2003

EXTRA-CURRICULAR **COURSES**

Programming with Google Go Specialization University of California, Irvine on Coursera, 24h.

Data Science Math Skills

Duke University on Coursera, 13h.

Digital Product Management: Modern Fundamentals 2020

2021

2021

	University of Virginia on Coursera, 16h.	
	Fundamentals of Project Planning and Management University of Virginia on Coursera, 8h.	2018
	O setor de games no Brasil: panorama, carreiras e oportunidades Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, 30h.	2018
	Introduction to User Experience Design Georgia Institute of Technology on Coursera, 10h.	2017
	Gamification University of Pennsylvania on Coursera, 48h.	2016
	A complexidade sensível: Um paralelo entre videogames e arte Universidade Estadual de Campinas on Coursera, 14h.	2016
	Oil & Gas Industry Operations and Markets Duke University on Coursera, 10h.	2016
	Geologia do petróleo para não-geólogos ABGP - Associação Brasileira de Geólogos do Petróleo, 20h.	2014
CERTIFICA- TIONS	Certified Scrum Product Owner Valid: Mar 20 Certifier: Scrum Alliance License: 000304959	14 - Mar 2024
	rtified Scrum Master rtifier: Scrum Alliance License: 000304959 Valid: Jan 2014 - Mar 2024	
EXTRA- CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES	Co-organizer of PUC-Rio's Global Game Jam Helped organize PUC-Rio's Global Game Jam. Jan 2	018, Jan 2020
	Volunteer reviewer for Entertainment Computing 2016 - Present Volunteer reviewer for Entertainment Computing, an Elsevier journal. ISSN 1875-9521.	
	Researcher at PUC-Rio's Game Design Research Group 2013 - Present Associate researcher in the Arts & Design Department research group under prof. Maria das Graças Chagas advisory. Themes include player-NPC relationship and artificial intelligence.	
	SBGames 2011's Independent Games Festival contestant Contestant with the game Lights Out. Awarded with the third place in p in the Art Game cathegory.	2011 people's choice
CAMEC		0011

A puzzle-like art game for 2 players made in GameMaker 8.1. Presented at SBGames 2011, FILE Games 2012, Festival Games Brasil 2013. Role: programmer (GameMaker

Seu Espião Safado!

Scripting Language) and 2D artist.

 $Lights\ Out$

GAMES

2011

A print-and-play dice game for 3 players where 2 agents are trying to uncover a spy's secret (Brazilian Portuguese only). Role: game designer.

You Are Trash! 2009

A Java 2D game mix of puzzle and platformer, made in the Gamerama project. Role: programmer and game designer.

RPG

Encontros Aleatórios: O Bando da Pena Vermelha, In: Forbidden Magazine #12, Buró Brasil, 2021. Link

Encontros Aleatórios: A Estalagem Lebre Confortável, In: Forbidden Magazine #9, Buró Brasil, 2021. Link

Ser Mago pra Quê?, In: Forbidden Magazine #4, Buró Brasil, 2020. Link

Zen e a Arte de Armadilhas, In: Forbidden Magazine #2, Buró Brasil, 2020. Link

Delírios de X'agyg: Episódio 1 - A Balada de Baleem Altrafer, Editor: Rafael Beltrame, RedBox Editora, 2017. Link

OTHER

Personal homepage: http://killerasus.github.io INFORMATION LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/brunobaere/